<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

   <statements version="1.0" htmlParse="false">
     <statement id="1">1.Evaluate and manage patients presenting with acute respiratory failure, including early recognition, diagnostic evaluation, and treatment of most likely causes including pneumonia, obstructive lung disease exacerbation, congestive heart failure, pulmonary embolism and tension pneumothorax.</statement>
     <statement id="2">2.Evaluate and manage patients with sepsis and septic shock, including early recognition, resuscitation, appropriate antibiotics, and systematic evaluation for source control.</statement>
     <statement id="3">3.Evaluate and manage common nephrology conditions in the ICU, including acute kidney injury, renal replacement therapy, and acid base and electrolyte disorders.</statement>
     <statement id="4">4. Provide compassionate, patient-centered care, engaging with patients and family members in shared decision making using collaborative communication skills, empathy, and respect.</statement>
     <statement id="5">5. Evaluate and manage patients presenting with acute common cardiovascular conditions, including arrhythmias, acute coronary syndromes, valvular heart disease, congestive heart failure, and vascular emergencies.</statement>
     <statement id="6">6. Evaluate and manage patients with shock, including early recognition, rapid diagnostic evaluation, and targeted treatment of cardiogenic, hypovolemic/hemorrhagic, distributive and obstructive shock, including targeted vasopressor management.</statement>
     <statement id="7">7. Evaluate and manage patients presenting with poisoning or overdose, including complications of alcohol, drug intoxication and withdrawal.</statement>
     <statement id="8">8. Evaluate and manage common gastroenterology conditions in the ICU, including acute gastrointestinal hemorrhage, difficile colitis, bowel obstruction and perforation, complications of hepatobiliary disease, and pancreatitis.</statement>
     <statement id="9">9.Evaluate and manage common hematology and oncology conditions in the ICU, including coagulopathy, acute / massive hemorrhage, common malignancies and their associated complications.</statement>
     <statement id="10">10. Evaluate and manage common neurologic conditions in the ICU, including encephalopathy, seizure, stroke, and intracranial hemorrhage.</statement>
     <statement id="11">11. Identify, evaluate and manage patients with ARDS, collaborating with Respiratory Therapy and utilizing institutional protocols to deliver safe and effective lung protective ventilation, rapidly identify patients with refractory hypoxemia, and appropriately employ early liberation strategies.</statement>
     <statement id="12">12. Resuscitate and stabilize critically ill patients, performing necessary diagnostic and therapeutic interventions in a timely manner and effectively coordinating care with the interprofessional critical care team and appropriate consultants.</statement>
     <statement id="13">13. Safely and efficiently perform procedures common to the practice of critical care medicine, and demonstrate understanding of indications, contraindications, limitations, and complications of these interventions.</statement>
     <statement id="14">14. Diagnose and manage acute pain in critical illness and the perioperative setting, including appropriate use of opioids, non-opioid analgesics, and assessment scales.</statement>
     <statement id="15">15. Evaluate and manage common critical care infections, including meningitis/encephalitis, pneumonia, catheter related bloodstream infections, simple and complicated biliary, urinary tract, skin and soft tissue infections, and opportunistic pathogens commonly seen in immune compromised hosts.</statement>
     <statement id="16">16. Professional, respectful and timely in the execution of all clinical activities, with appropriate communication and collaboration within interprofessional team.</statement>
     <statement id="17">17. Ensures effective transitions of care through consistent, concise communication of patient care plans and recommendations.</statement>
     <statement id="18">18. Leads efficient and effective ICU rounds by soliciting and incorporating collaborative input from the interprofessional team, appropriate consulting services, patients and families to develop a well-organized, appropriate plan of care.</statement>
     <statement id="19">19. Efficiently employ critical care protocols and checklists to prevent common critical care complications, and effectively diagnose and manage delirium, venous thromboembolism, nosocomial infections, malnutrition, hyperglycemia, decubitus ulcers, and musculoskeletal complications.</statement>
     <statement id="20">20. Evaluate and manage perioperative patients and common post-surgical complications.</statement>
   </statements>